Okay, so maybe you got a tad bit lost in
the code logic there on that last video
and that is totally understandable. So
what I'm going to show you today is
something that will help you to um work
your way through code bit by bit. It
also is really helpful for when you have
errors. So I'm going to show you how to
use the Chrome debugging tool. Um so
here I have Google Chrome and I have it
opened to the file that I'm currently
working on. So, it's going to ask my
letter grade for class one,
two, three, and four. Says great job.
There's your GPA. Well, if you want to
um use the Chrome um debugging tool,
which is really, really good, then
you'll use if you're on a Windows,
you'll hit control shift I, or if you're
on a Mac, you'll hit command option I
and then regardless of which one you
used, you will now click on this source
column. And this source tab, it should
look really familiar because this is
just the code that you just wrote. Um,
and it's just displaying it here. The
very cool thing about this is I can
click on the number here and it will
give me um what's called a break point.
A breakpoint means stop the code from
running and pause right here and then
give me control of the code. So I can
control how it runs from here on out.
Um, so to demonstrate this in action,
once you've clicked, um, you'll want to
click on either a line that actually has
code on it. So in this case, line 16
actually has some code that's doing some
processing. And if it's doing
processing, then you can pause it. So
we're going to put a break point there.
And then what we're going to do is we're
going to reload the page. And you'll
notice rather than immediately popping
up my popup like it used to, it is now
paused and it said, "Okay, we are on
line 16." the highlighted portion of
line 16 is about to run. So, right now,
counter is not set to anything. In fact,
if we come over here, um, we've got this
little thing called scope. If you open
up scope, it'll show you all of the
variables that you have. We'll talk a
little bit about scope more in the
future, but for now, um, you can see
that you have a variable called counter,
and it has no value.
Now up here you've got some controls for
controlling your loop. Um this one right
here is the one I most often use. It's
called step into. Um the difference
between step over and step into is a
little too nuanced at this point in the
course. Um but for now I would just work
on the step into function. So I'm going
to click this button and it's going to
run the very next step of code. It
basically means run the next step. So it
runs the next step.
um and we said for let counter equal
zero. So now if we come to our block, we
can see that counter is now zero. So it
was undefined. Now it's zero. So it
first set our counter. Now we're looking
at what the next step that's highlighted
is. Is counter less than four? Well, 0
is less than four. So we should expect
this loop to run. So it's going to check
this condition. Uh you can hover over
counter and see that it's zero. It's
going to say is 0 less than four? zero
is less than four. So if we click the
next button, it drops into the for loop.
So now we're inside of these curly
braces
and it says let letter grade equal
prompt what is your letter grade for
counter which is zero. Counter + 1. So 0
+ 1 is one. So we should expect if we
hit this next button and say run line
18, we should see the prompt show up
with what is your letter grade for class
one. So we'll hit next. It says what is
your letter grade for class one? I'm
going to type B+ in here and then I'm
going to hit okay. Now that I've done
that, if I hover over letter grade, you
can see that it's now set to B+. It was
set to nothing and now it's set to B+.
In fact, over here you can see that GPA
is set to nothing. But we're about to
run this line of code. When we run this
line of code, it'll take GPA from being
set to unavailable to GPA being set to
zero. So over here, you can either hit
F11 or you can hit the next button. If
you hit the next button, you can see
that GPA is now zero. So over here we
can see letter grade is B+, GPA is zero.
So then we can see how it evaluates an
if statement. So it comes here to the
first if statement and says is B+ equal
to A? B+ is not equal to A. So we should
expect it to skip over those curly
braces and go straight to line 24.
And it did. Now we're seeing if B+ is
equal to A minus. It's not. So, we
should expect to see it skip straight to
line 27.
Okay, now it's going to see if B+ is
equal to B+. It is. So, we should expect
to see it run line 28 rather than
skipping it like it did the previous
few. And then once it's done to skip all
the way to the end to line 57. So, we'll
hit the next button. We'll drop in. Our
GPA
um is right now zero, but if we run this
next line of code, our GPA has changed
to 3.3, which is what we expected. And
now we're on line 57. So, it was able to
skip over all of the additional else and
the else because one of the conditions
evaluated to true. So, now our total GPA
started at zero and now we're going to
add on 3.3. So, we're going to hit the
next button and boom, our total GPA is
3.3. And now it jumps up to the top and
comes here to this counter. So, right
now counter is zero, but it's about to
execute the part that's highlighted,
which is this plus+. Plus+, if you
remember, I said says increment it by
one. So, if we hit the next button,
counter is now one and one is less than
four.
um which means we should expect the loop
to run. So it's going to drop into the
loop and it's about to prompt what is
your letter grade for class. The counter
is one. 1 + 1 is two. So we should
expect the prompt to say what is your
letter grade grade for class 2.
And I'm going to give it um an A so you
can see how that works. Um
so letter grade is an A. GPA um was
previously set to 3.3,
but now we've reset it back to zero.
Our letter grade is A, so we should
expect it to run line 22 and then skip
all the way to the end of the if
statement. So, it runs line 22 and skips
to the end of the if statement. Our GPA
is four. Take total GPA, which was 3.3,
and then add on four.
Now, if you've run through your loop a
couple of times, you can determine,
let's say you had an error, but your
loop is running perfectly, then you can
determine everything in this loop works.
I don't need to test this loop anymore.
So, what you can do, you can put a break
point on line 61, and you can scroll up
to line 16 and take your break point
off. And now you can say, okay, run
through line 63.
And then you'll hit the blue play
button. So when I do this, it'll ask me
for my letter grade for class 3, which
we'll do C minus.
And then it automatically, it didn't
pause the loop at all. It just jumped
straight through it and said, "What is
your letter grade for class 4?" So the
letter grade for class 4, we'll put in
another A. And then it paused. It paused
on the line that I told it I wanted to
pause on. Because I'd run through the
loop twice, I was confident my loop
worked. So now I come here and I can see
that total GPA is 13.
That's not a real GPA. That's just the
sum of each of the GPA. Now, we need to
divide it by the number of classes that
we took. And in this case, we took four
classes. So, if we take our total GPA
and divide it by four and we hit the
next button, now our GPA is 3.25.
So, I'm going to show you a little trick
here.
We if you want to test your if statement
and you don't want to run all of the
math to figure out um what GPA
combination will give you 3.3 or 2.3.
Right now 3.25
is not going to trigger this first if
statement. But maybe I want to see if
the code I wrote in that first if
statement works.
Well, because we've paused our code, we
can actually execute some JavaScript
here. So, um, you can come over here on
the left hand panel and double click on
total GPA and it says 3.25, but we
really want to check if it's if greater
than 3.3 works. So, what we're going to
do is we're just going to edit this
value live. Ignore all the previous
calculations and just edit this value so
we can test the value. So, let's test if
exactly 3.3 works. So, now total GPA is
3.3. if you hover over it. So, we're
seeing if 3.3 is greater than or equal
to 3.3 because we've now edited this
value from what it was originally. We
can now force the condition to happen
and we can test our code. So, if I hit
the next button, now it was 3.25, but
I've changed it to 3.3. So, this
condition evaluates to true. So, now I'm
going to get an alert that my total GPA
is 3.3. Great job. Whatever the rest of
that message says. So, if I hit the next
button, says your GPA is 3.3. Great job.
Your consistent effort is paying off.
Keep challenging yourself and building
on this progress. You'll hit okay, and
it'll jump to the end of your script
because you'll see everything else is
just comments. So, there was nothing for
it to pause on. Now, if you were not
using live server, that would be the end
of the code and it would just show you
your home screen. Because we're using
live server, liveserver has some extra
JavaScript that it wrote and wrote in
there and you can just ignore that. So
that's all of this stuff right here. And
so to just get back to your main
website, you just hit this play button
and boom, everything went as expected.
And so that is how you use the debugger.
I heavily encourage you to use it to
step through complicated logic. Anytime
you get stuck and you're confused about
how something is working, step through
it with a debugger and see if you can
guess where it's going to go next. And
that wraps up this section on the Chrome
debugger. Thanks for watching.